what we will look at now is one of the
simpler coherence protocols called MSI
in MSI a block can be in one of three
states in a cache I stands for the
invalid State a block is in an invalid
State either when it is present in the
cache but its valid bit would not be set
or when it's simply not present in the
cach so a block that is not present in
the cach is treated like it is present
but in an invalid State s stands for the
shared State a block that is in the
shared state in a cache can be read
without any further Ado but if we write
it we have to do something a local read
to a block that is in the shared State
keeps the Block in the shared State and
doesn't do anything else and finally m
stands for the modified state in this
state we can read the block just like in
the shared State without sending
anything out and we can also write to
this block by the local core without
sending anything out now because this is
an invalidation based protocol what
happens is in the modify State we are
sure that there are no other cached
copies which is why we are allowed to
locally write we don't have to tell
anybody that we are writing because we
know there is nobody so this is sort of
equivalent to having valid equals 1 and
dirty equals 1
in a normal cache we just call this
state modified because it's easier to
understand what's going on this way then
if we have to look at individual bits
and we will see that with more
complicated coherence protocols we will
add maybe a state or two but we would
need to add several bits in order to
track what's going on so now in the
invalid State we have what's equivalent
to valid bit being zero pretty much we
behave like we don't have the block
either because we really don't have it
or because we have it
but we are not supposed to read it or
write it so when we have a write and the
block is in the invalid State we move
the block to the modified state so when
we have a local write meaning the local
processor wants to write and the block
is in the invalid State we move the
block to the modified state but we
cannot just do that to do that we have
to put the right request on the bus so
pretty much this is a right Miss we have
to tell others that it's a right Miss we
get the data and now we can put it in
the modified State why well because our
right request on the bus pretty much
made sure that nobody else has a copy
anymore cuz the right request that we
made invalidated everybody else if we
have a block in the modified State and
we observe on the bus that another cach
is placing a right on the bus then we
will go to the invalid state so we do
this when we Snoop the right on the bus
and we cannot just do this and be done
when we Snoop a right on the bus because
we are in the modified state where we
have the dirty copy meaning really the
only fresh copy of the data in the
system is in our cache it's not even in
memory cuz it's dirty here we have to
write the block back as we're
transitioning to invalid and we have to
delay the data that would be sent to the
right request until we are done with the
right back this can be done in two ways
one is to actually cancel that request
write back move to invalid and then that
request gets repeated and now gets the
data from memory another one is when we
see a write on the bus if it's
requesting data then what we do is we
suppress the memory response and feed
the data to that processor the simpler
way of doing things is just to delay
that request right back and then let it
proceed but either way we have to make
sure that before we move from modifi to
invalid we write back the data to memory
and also make sure that the right
request if it is a right Miss and needs
the data gets our new data not the data
from memory now if we Snoop a read on
the bus and we are in the modified State
then we move to the shared state so we
have snooped a read on the bus we will
now not be the only one who has a copy
of the data that means we will not be
able to write without telling others so
we will move to the shared state
just like here we have to also make sure
that the block is written back the
shared state is equivalent to having V
equals 1 and D equal Z so we will not be
doing a write back from our shared State
cuz it only allows reads anyway so as we
are moving from the dirty to a clean
State modified to Shared we're going to
write back the data the reading
processor wants a copy of this block
again we have to either the delay that
request do a right back change to the
shared State and then let that processor
proceed with a read or we have to
suppress the memory response that would
happen as a result of this read and
provide our data instead as we are
transitioning to the shared state if the
processor reads a block and the block is
in the invalid State then the block will
be moved to a shared state so in
response to a local read we put a read
request on the bus and then we get the
data and then we are in the shared state
for that data note that the data might
come from memory or it may come from
another cache because it had the data in
the modified State and we needed to get
that data but as far as this local cache
is concerned it puts a read request on
the bus it gets the data and then it
puts that block in the shared state in
the local cache then we can do many
reads without telling anybody if we have
a block in the shared state and we
observe a snoop right on the bus then we
move the block to the invalid State we
don't have to do anything because the
block is clean as far as we are
concerned we don't have to write it back
we simply have to do the equivalent of
resetting the valid bit and move to the
invalid state so there is nothing really
that we have to do except change the
state so that next time we try to read
it we can no longer read it here we have
to put a read request on the bus again
if we Snoop a read on the bus in the
shared state we don't need to do
anything why well because our shared
state is okay with there being other
sharers that are only going to read the
data and finally although local reads
are okay in the shared state if we have
a local right that is not allowed in the
shared state so a local right that finds
the Block in the shared state will make
us move the block to a modified state
but we cannot do that silently we cannot
just move the block and write to it what
we have to do is put an invalidation on
the bus know that things are slightly
different when we move from invalid
State on a local right to modified and
when we moved from shared state to a
modified State on a local right here we
put a right request that asks for a
block so that we can write it here we
already have the block this is the most
upto-date copy because if there was
another right after that we would not
have it in the shared state so now we
want to write to it we already have the
data we just need to put an invalidation
request on the bus so this invalidation
request does not actually request the
data it just puts a request on the bus
for everybody to invalidate their copies
but it's not asking for the data so
pretty much as soon as we put risk
request on the bus we can write because
by putting an invalidation on the bus we
have made sure that now everybody is
invalidated at which point we are in the
modified State now of course in the
invalid State whatever we Snoop for this
block on the bus doesn't matter we're
going to stay in the invalid State also
in the shared state it doesn't matter
whether we Snoop somebody's request to
write or an invalidation that they put
on the bus we still move to the invalid
State without doing much and finally
note that if we are in a modified State
we will observe a right if somebody
wants to write and not an invalidation
because if we are in the modified state
that means that everybody else is in the
invalid state for this block so if they
want to write they'll have to put a
right request on the bus they cannot be
in the shared State and put just an
invalidation out